# Gianmaria Del Monte

SOFTWARE ENGINEER

Geneva - Switzerland

 ¶ +41 078 225 24 27

 | ■ gianmaria.del.monte@cern.ch

 | ■ github.com/gmgigi96

in linkedin.com/in/gianmaria-del-monte-81575b162



### **Personal Profile**

Diligent Software Engineer with passion of designing and developing highly scalable software systems. Excellent attention to details and problem solving, with an innate ability to learn and master new technologies. Experience in software development's life cycle, including designing, coding, testing, delivery and maintenance. Keen to use my skills to push the frontiers of science and technology.

#### **Education**

**MEDILS** Split, Croatia

Thematic CERN School of Computing

• Held on Security of research computing infrastructures

**Rome Tre University** Rome, Italy

M.Sc. in Computer Engineering 2019 - 2020

- Thesis title: Scaling blockchains without giving up decentralization and security • Thesis supervisor: Prof. Maurizio Pizzonia
- · Final mark: 110/110 with honors

**Rome Tre University** Rome, Italy

B.Sc. in Computer Engineering 2016 - 2018

- Thesis title: Implementation of an efficient protocol for data integrity on Cloud
- Thesis supervisor: Prof. Maurizio Pizzonia
- Final mark: 110/110 with honors

## Work Experience

**CERN** Geneva, Switzerland

Software Engineer

Jan 2021 - Present

Nov 2018 - Jul 2020

- · Proactively support and maintain the CERNBox software ecosystem to provide a highly reliable service for more than 37K users, holding 18PB
- Design, implementation and deployment of a new backup system for CERNBox/cephfs (24/7, 600M daily file ingest)
- · Engagement with the open source community (Reva) to provide various bug-fixes and major enhancements (Lock APIs, federated shares)
- Ensuring day-to-day operational activities are carried out in a timely and reliable way
- · Supervision of a summer student to implement self-restore functionalities to address user community demand
- · Coordination among other team members of successful delivery of service improvements, specially on the server side
- Support CERN IT Security Team as second line member to ensure Organization security
- Technical Skills: Go, Python, CentOS, Puppet, Bash, Git, MySQL, gRPC, REST APIs, EOS, distributed systems

**Roma Tre University** Rome, Italy

Teaching assistant

· Teaching assistant for Fundamentals of Computer Science course for the bachelor degree in Computer Engineering

• Technical Skills: Java, C, data structures and algorithms, memory allocation

**Roma Tre University** Rome, Italy

Software Engineer Oct 2019 - Nov 2019

- Designed and implemented a mobile app that streamlines every aspect of student life at ROme Tre University, from booking a spot in the library, scheduling exams and real-time notifications about lecture delays and cancellations
- Technical Skills: Java, Android

## **Projects**

R3busFormazione Rome, Italy

Roma Tre University

 A web application to manage a training centre supporting local authentication and OAuth, automatically deployed on Heroku through CircleCI, realized in Spring Boot and Java

Pipeline Integrity Rome, Italy

Roma Tre University 2018

· Implementation of an efficient protocol for data integrity, realized with actor model, using Akka Framework and Kotlin

#### Skills

**Programming** Java, Go, Python, C, Dart, Kotlin

Miscellaneous Linux, Shell (Bash/Zsh), ŁTEX, Git, Spring, Flutter, MySQL, PostgreSQL, Redis, MongoDB, Puppet, Docker, Distributed storage

systems (EOS), distribute programming, desing patterns, design architectures

**Soft Skills** Time Management, Teamwork, Problem-solving, communication, positive attitude, self-supervising, team leadership

### **Achievements**

2019	<b>3rd place</b> , Local competitions of CyberChallenge 2019	Italy
2019	4th place, National competitions of CyberChallenge 2019	Italy
2018	Elite, Luca Raso scholarship for best students enrolled in Master's degree in Computer Engineering at Roma	Italv
	Tre University.	rtuty
2016	Winner, Scholarship for best average grade in the Engineering Department of Roma Tre University.	Italy

### **Publications**

Scaling blockchains without giving up decentralization and security: A solution to the blockchain scalability trilemma Gianmaria Del Monte, Diego Pennino, Maurizio Pizzonia

Proceedings of the 3rd Workshop on Cryptocurrencies and Blockchains for Distributed Systems, 2020

### **Conferences**

C(ERN) BACK(UP): consolidated multi-petabyte backup solution for heterogenous storage and filesystems Gianmaria Del Monte, Elizaveta Ragozina, Roberto Valverde Cameselle

CS3 2023 - Cloud Storage Synchronization and Sharing, 2023, https://indico.cern.ch/event/1210538/contributions/5207944

Applications integration beyond local clouds with OCM

Giuseppe Lo Presti, Gianmaria Del Monte, Michiel De Jong

 $CS3\,2023-Cloud\,Storage\,Synchronization\,and\,Sharing,\,2023, \\ \texttt{https://indico.cern.ch/event/1210538/contributions/5206694}$ 

User-friendly OCM Invitation and Sharing: OCIS, CERNBox

Elizaveta Ragozina, Gianmaria Del Monte, Samuel Alfageme Sainz

 ${\it CS3\,2023\,-\,Cloud\,Storage\,Synchronization\,and\,Sharing}, 2023, {\it https://indico.cern.ch/event/1210538/contributions/5208014}, {\it https://indico.cern.ch/event/1210538/contributions/520801$ 

CERNBox backup evolution

Gianmaria Del Monte, Roberto Valverde Cameselle

 $\it 6th\ EOS\ workshop, 2022, https://indico.cern.ch/event/1103358/contributions/4758282$ 

Visualizing physics data in ownCloud Infinite Scale

Gianmaria Del Monte

own Cloud Conference, 2021, https://cfp.owncloud.com/occon2021/talk/W8KHKM

## **Languages** \_

English Professional proficiency
Italian Native proficiency
French Basic knowledge